MAURICIO APABLAZA

La Huerta 8105, Vitacura, Chile. Postcode: 7640259. Tel: +56 9 33024783. Email: mapablaza@gmail.com

Mauricio Apablaza is director of research at the School of Government at the Universidad del Desarrollo, Chile, research associate of the Oxford Poverty and Human Development Initiative (OPHI) at Oxford University and Visiting Fellow at the International Inequalities Institute at London School of Economics and Political Science (LSE). Mauricio is also the director of the programme Conocimiento e Investigación en Personas Mayores (CIPEM) and president of the Chilean Commission for Quality of Employment and former member of the Chilean commission of experts on informal labour.

Previously, he worked as Research Officer and Outreach Coordinator at OPHI, at the University of Oxford. Mauricio has been regional director for civil society organizations and consultant to international businesses and agencies (MEDSTAT/OECD, UNDP, SADC, WORLD BANK). He supported national teams in the construction of multidimensional poverty measures and led training programmes in South Africa, Malaysia, Indonesia, Jordan, Egypt, Hungary, Brazil, Chile, the Netherlands, Barbados, US, Vietnam, Nicaragua, and Thailand, among others.

He has published articles in PLOS ONE, World Development, Journal of Ethnic and Migration Studies, the Review of Income and Wealth, among others. He teaches applied microeconomics and quantitative methods (STATA & R) at the undergraduate and graduate level (Masters and PhD) at Universidad del Desarrollo. Mauricio holds a PhD in Economics from the University of Nottingham and a postdoc at the University of Oxford. His research areas and publications focus on inequality, poverty, multidimensionality, and wellbeing dynamics.

Currently:

- Director of Research, Facultad de Gobierno, Universidad del Desarrollo, Chile
- Research associate, OPHI, International Development Department, University of Oxford, UK
- Research fellow, III, London School of Economics and Social Science, UK

Academic Background:

- Post-doctorate, OPHI, University of Oxford
- PhD in economics, School of Economics, University of Nottingham
- Master of Public policy (MPP), Universidad del Desarrollo, Chile
- Bachelor of business and economics, Universidad del Desarrollo, Chile

Selected Publications (peer reviewed articles)

- Núñez-Franz, L., Ramírez-Santana, M., Rubilar, P., Vial, C., Apablaza, M., González, C., ... & Aguilera, X. (2023). Seroprevalence of Natural and Acquired Immunity against the SARS-CoV-2 Virus in a Population Cohort from Two Chilean Cities, 2020–2022. *Viruses*, 15(1), 201.
- Vial, P. A., González, C., Apablaza, M., Vial, C., Lavín, M. E., Araos, R., ... & Aguilera, X. (2022). First wave of SARS-CoV-2 in Santiago Chile: Seroprevalence, asymptomatic infection and infection fatality rate. Epidemics, 40, 100606.
- Aguilera, X.; González, C.; Apablaza, M.; Rubilar, P.; Icaza, G.; Ramírez-Santana, M.; Pérez, C.; Cortes, L.J.; Núñez-Franz, L.; Quezada-Gaete, R.; Castillo-Laborde, C.; Correa, J.; Said, M.; Hormazábal, J.; Vial, C.; Vial, P. (2022). Immunization and SARS-CoV-2 Antibody Seroprevalence in a Country with High Vaccination Coverage: Lessons from Chile. Vaccines 2022, 10, 1002.
- Apablaza, M., Sehnbruch, K., González, P., & Méndez, R. (2022). Regional inequality in multidimensional quality of employment: insights from Chile, 1996–2017. Regional Studies, 1-18.
- Aguilera, X., Hormazábal, J., Vial, C., Cortes, L. J., González, C., Rubilar, P., ... & Vial, P. (2022). SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing antibodies in Chile after a vaccination campaign with five different schemes. Vaccines, 10(7), 1051.
- Vial, P., González, C., Icaza, G., Ramirez-Santana, M., Quezada-Gaete, R., Núñez-Franz, Apablaza, M. & Aguilera, X. (2022). Seroprevalence, spatial distribution, and social determinants of SARS-CoV-2 in three urban centers of Chile. BMC Infectious Diseases, 22(1), 1-16.
- González, P., Sehnbruch, K., Apablaza, M., Méndez Pineda, R., & Arriagada, V. (2021). A multidimensional approach to measuring quality of employment (QoE) deprivation in six central American countries. Social Indicators Research, 158(1), 107-141
- Guerrero, M., Mandakovic, V., Apablaza, M., & Arriagada, V. (2021). Are migrants in/from emerging economies more entrepreneurial than natives?. International Entrepreneurship and Management Journal, 17(2), 527-548.
- Sehnbruch, K., González, P., Apablaza, M., Méndez, R., & Arriagada, V. (2020). The Quality of Employment (QoE) in nine Latin American countries: A multidimensional perspective. World Development, 127, 104738.
- Delgado, I., Cabieses, B., Apablaza, M., Castillo, C., Aguilera, X., Matute, I. & Benach, J. (2019). Evaluation of the effectiveness and equity of the maternity protection reform in Chile from 2000 to 2015. PloS one, 14(9)
- von Bloh, J., Mandakovic, V., Apablaza, M., Amorós, J. E., & Sternberg, R. (2018). Transnational entrepreneurs: opportunity or necessity driven? Empirical evidence from two dynamic economies from Latin America and Europe. Journal of Ethnic and Migration Studies, 1-19.
- Florenzano, R., Apablaza, M., Hernandez, I., Carstens, C., Bortolaso, M., & Roizblatt, A. (2018). Mental health of inmigrants in santiago de chile: the use of the culturally focused interview (cfi) in attenders of public health services. In international journal of behavioral medicine (Vol. 25, pp. S72-S73). 233 Spring St, New York, Ny 10013 Usa: Springer.
- Alkire, S., Apablaza, M., Chakravarty, S., & Yalonetzky, G. (2017). Measuring chronic multidimensional poverty. Journal of Policy Modeling, 39(6), 983-1006.

- Dussaillant, F., & Apablaza, M. (2017). Predicting posttraumatic stress symptom prevalence and local distribution after an earthquake with scarce data. Prehospital and disaster medicine, 32(4), 357-367.
- Alkire, S. and Apablaza, M. (2016). "Multidimensional poverty in Europe 2006–2012: Illustrating a methodology." in Atkinson, A. B., Guio, A. C., & Marlier, E. (Eds.). (2017). *Monitoring social inclusion in Europe*. Luxembourg: Publications Office of the European Union.
- Apablaza, M., Bresson, F., & Yalonetzky, G. (2016). When More Does Not Necessarily Mean Better: Health-Related Illfare Comparisons with Non-Monotone Well-Being Relationships. Review of Income and Wealth, 62, S145-S178. Chicago
- Gerlitz, J. Y., Apablaza, M., Hoermann, B., Hunzai, K., & Bennett, L. (2015). A multidimensional poverty measure for the Hindu Kush–Himalayas, applied to selected districts in Nepal. Mountain Research and Development, 35(3), 278-288.

Academic Experience

Treadenne Emp	chence
2015 - 2019	Lecturer (Universidad del Desarrollo, Chile)
	 Quantitative methods for Social Sciences (PhD in Social Complexity)
	 Human development and capability approach (Master of Public Policies)
	Economics and Industrial Organization (MBA)
	Public Policies (Master in Health Management)
	 Microeconomics, Macroeconomics and impact evaluation (Undergraduate)
2011- 2014	OPHI facilitator
	• Instructor of training in multidimensional poverty theory and methodologies in more than 20 countries such as Nepal, UK, Jordan, Chile, Thailand, Egypt, Hungary, Malaysia, Vietnam, South Africa, Brazil, Netherlands, Nicaragua, US and Barbados, among others.
2010 - 2011	Lecturer (University of Nottingham, Malaysia Campus)
	Quantitative Economics
2009 - 2011	Graduate Teacher Assistant (University of Nottingham) GTA Teaching Excellence Award 2009-2010
	 International Trade II (Prof. Rod Falvey)
	 Introduction to Microeconomics (Dr. Morgan)
	 Current Economic Issues (Prof. Richard Disney, Dr. Kauppi and Dr. Wright)
	 Current Economic Issues II (Prof. David Greenaway)
2006 - 2007	Lecturer (Universidad del Desarrollo, Chile)
	 Among other: Microeconomics, Macroeconomics, Entrepreneurship, and International Economics
1997 - 2003	Tutor at undergraduate programmes (Universidad del Desarrollo, Chile)
	Among others: Accounting, Microeconomics, Macroeconomics, International Economics, Political
2002 2005	Economy, and Finance II/III
2002 - 2005	Economics Teacher (St. Johns School, Chile)
	International Baccalaureate Program

Professional Experience

1 Totessional Experience	
2000-2003	Regional Manager – "Un techo para Chile", Chile. http://www.untechoparachile.cl
2001	Consultant. Project "Balanced Scorecard". Electric centrals Buenos Aires, Chocón, and Costanera - Argentina
2002	Consultant new projects – Welfare Department. Chilean Navy, Chile.
2002 -2003	General Manager "ASERCOM Ltda." Concepción, Chile.
2002 -2007	Vice-Chancellor of Academic Affairs Assistant. Universidad del Desarrollo. Santiago, Chile
2004 - 2007	Researcher Centre for Public Policies, http://cpp.udd.cl, Santiago, Chile.
	Consultant Public Policies and Management. Local Governments and Members of the Chilean Parliament.
2011 - 2012	Teaching Fellow, Department of Economics, University of Nottingham, UK.
2010 -	Research Officer, Oxford Poverty and Human Development Initiative (OPHI), Department of International
	Development. University of Oxford, UK.
2012 - 2013	Outreach Coordinator, Oxford Poverty and Human Development Initiative (OPHI), Department of
	International Development. University of Oxford, UK.

Other Publications

- Alkire, S., Apablaza, M., & Guio, A. C. (2021). Chronic multidimensional poverty in Europe. In Improving the understanding of poverty and social exclusion in Europe (pp. 275-292). Publications Office of the European Union.
- Apablaza, M. & Hisarciklilar, M. (2013) 'Inter-Generational Mobility In Eastern Europe And Central Asia'. World Bank.
- Apablaza, M.; Yalonetzky, G. (2013). "Multidimensional Chronic Poverty or Chronic Multidimensional Deprivation". OPHI Research in Progress 34a. Oxford Poverty and Human Development Initiative. University of Oxford.
- Apablaza, M.; Yalonetzky, G. (2013) Young Lives Working Paper 101. Decomposing Multidimensional Poverty Dynamics.
 Young Lives, Department of International Development at the University of Oxford, Oxford, UK (2013)
- Apablaza, M., Ocampo, J.P., & Yalonetzky, G. (2010). 'Decomposing Changes in Multidimensional Poverty in 10 Countries', mimeo, Oxford Poverty and Human Development Initiative, University of Oxford.